<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Come out of her my people] or an ansvver to the questions of a gentlevvoman (a professour in the Antichristian Church of England) about hearing the publicke ministers vvhere it is largely discussed and proved to be sinfull and unlavvfull. Also a iust apologie for the way of total separation (commonly but falsely called Brownisme) that it is the truth of God, though lightly esteemed in the eyes of the blinde world. With a challenge to dispute with them publickly before King &amp; Counsell: to prove whatsoever I said at the pillery against them. Viz. that the calling of them all is jure diabolo: even from the divell himselfe. By mee John Lilburne. Close prisoner in the Fleete for the cause of Christ.</title>
            <title>Come out of her my people.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15596</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107364</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843066</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843066</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7774</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05464)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7774)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 584:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Come out of her my people] or an ansvver to the questions of a gentlevvoman (a professour in the Antichristian Church of England) about hearing the publicke ministers vvhere it is largely discussed and proved to be sinfull and unlavvfull. Also a iust apologie for the way of total separation (commonly but falsely called Brownisme) that it is the truth of God, though lightly esteemed in the eyes of the blinde world. With a challenge to dispute with them publickly before King &amp; Counsell: to prove whatsoever I said at the pillery against them. Viz. that the calling of them all is jure diabolo: even from the divell himselfe. By mee John Lilburne. Close prisoner in the Fleete for the cause of Christ.</title>
                  <title>Come out of her my people.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Richt Right Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare of hope, of Englands purgation, &amp; the prelates dissolution. Anno 1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and press's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; cropped at head, affecting title and some page numbers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Brownists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7774:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7774:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> OR <hi>An Anſvver to the questions of a Gentlevvoman (a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsour in the Antichristian Church of England) about Hearing the Publicke Miniſters: vvhere it is largely diſcuſſed and proved to be ſinfull and vnlavvfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO A Iuſt Apologie for the way of Totall Separation (Commonly but falſly called Browniſme) That it is the truth of God, though lightly eſteemed in the eyes of the blinde world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With A Challenge to Diſpute with them publickly before King &amp; Counſell: to prove whatſoever J ſaid at the Pillery against them. Viz. That the Calling of them all is</hi> Jure Diabolo: <hi>Even from the Divell himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By mee JOHN LILBURNE. <hi>Cloſe Priſoner in the Fleete for the Cauſe of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>IOHN 10. Ver. 27.5.</bibl>
My Sheepe heare my voyce. For they know not the voyce of ſtrangers.</q>
            <p>Printed in the yeare of hope, of ENGLANDS purgation, &amp; the Prelates diſſolution. ANNO 1639.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7774:2"/>
            <head>The Publisher to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>COVRTEOVS READER:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT pleaſeth the Lord in this latter age of the world to giue vs ſundry helpes, whereby the man of ſinne, (with all that bloodie Crew) is more and more diſcovered: and Gods elect lead (as it were) by the hand out of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jf any therefore (ſhutting their eyes against the light) remaine not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding vnder the yoake of Antichriſt: they muſt make account to feele for it, the ſorer and heavier wrath of God.</p>
            <p>Touching this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> what it is, I ſhall leave it to thy triall and cenſure, and as thou findeſt profitt by the reading thereof, ſo bleſſe God for it, and be ready to communicate the good which thou receiveſt, vnto the profitt of others. Farewell and pray for mee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Who is thy truely loving friend and Countrie-man.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:7774:2"/>
            <head>Alvvayes give prayſe to God, and let him have the glory of all.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Ind and Loving Chriſtian Freind; J kindly ſalute you in our Lord and Saviour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> Beſeeching him, that his enlightning ſpirit, the Spirit of Truth, may both now and ever be with you, and remaine with you, and all thoſe that deſire to ſerve and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, in all his commandements, according to his revealed will, &amp; not according to mens precepts and devices, which is odious and abominable to him; <hi>Math.</hi> 15.9. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.9.10. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 66.3.</p>
            <p>But now to give an anſwer to that which you deſire, J ſay, and that in the words of truth, that the thing, as it is to me expreſſed, is very falſe, and therefore I have wrong done me by them that doe report it; and I would deſire you to know of my reſpected Freind the party that told you who they are that did report it.</p>
            <p>It ſeemes they ſay, that I have ſaid, that I would as ſoone heare the devill, as Doctor <hi>Stoughton,</hi> or M: <hi>Walker,</hi> which thing is very falſe, for I never ſaid it, nor medled with any particular perſons; But yet thus much J have ſaid, and ſtill doe affirme and maintaine, and will at all times be ready to make it good, and ſeale it with my blood: That the Prelates all of them are Limbs of the Beaſt, ſpoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 13 2. and alſo, that all thoſe Officers and Miniſters, that are made by them, are all of them Antichriſtian; the beſt as well as the worſt; And we have as good warrant to heare or give eare to the worſt, as well as the beſt; For I proved in my ſpeech, that the beſt of the Miniſters calling is as bad as the vvorſt of them; for they are all ſent by the Prelates, Chriſts profeſſed and knowne enemies, and they doe preach by vertue of their inſtituting of them, into the Office of Preiſthood, unto whoſe power they ſubmit and take an Oath of Canonicall odedience; And
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7774:3"/>
this doe the beſt among them, (as well as the worſt) that take upon them a Parochiall chardge, for they are not ſent from Chriſt, to preach the Goſpell, or by vertue of his power, which he hath left in the bodies of his particular (not Nationall) Churches, to chooſe or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine Officers to preach the Word; But by vertue of Antichriſts pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authority, from whom they have as really their calling and power given them to preach, as thoſe Officers that were ordained and inſtituted in the New Teſtament to preach Chriſts Goſpell, had their power from him; and this ere long you ſhall ſee fully proved, though I be never hereafter able to ſet pen to paper.</p>
            <p>Some thing concerning this I ſaid in my ſpeech, as in it you may reade, but it was but a little for the maine thing and ſtrength of my Argument, was behinde, which I could not make knowne, by reaſon of the Gagg; But J looke and expect to come there againe, or to a worſe place; and by the ſtrength and might of my God; I will, come life, come death; ſpeake my minde freely and couragiouſly; for I am ſtudying to fitt my ſelfe for it, and I doubt not but by the might of the Lord of Hoſts, who is my ſtrength and refuge, to reade them ſuch a Lecture, that ſhall make the Beaſt roare, and blaſpheme the God of Heaven for madneſſe, though I be hewen in peeces when I have done; For I feare neither the Devill, nor his Agents the Prelates, in this cauſe of my God, and the Lord hath ſheltred me under the ſhaddow of his wings, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91. under whoſe protection I am ſecure and ſafe from all danger and harme, for though it ſeaze upon me, yet ſhall it not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come me, therefore will I not feare what man can doe unto me, for God is my ſalvation, I will truſt, and not be affrayde, for the Lord <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah</hi> is become my ſalvation, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Exod.</hi> 15 2.</p>
            <p>I have in part, in a briefe way, ſince I was whipped, declared my minde and judgement to ſome freinds, becauſe I did feare falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, and I am alwayes ready, according to the command of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, to give an anſwer to every man that ſhall aſke me a reaſon of the hope that is in me, with meekeneſſe &amp; feare, 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 3 15.</p>
            <p>And J now deſire to impart a little of my minde unto you, but for my owne part I will perſwade no man to beleeve me, nor no man whatſoever, but only to beleeve <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> ſpeaking in the Scripture, it being the intire and abſolute rule of Faith, and that unerring touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, that is able to try gold from droſſe, neither would I have any to take upon them the profeſſion of that way, the truth of which I am fully convinced off; and am able to any man breathing for my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to give a reaſon, and grounded anſwer; But for others my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is to them, as one wiſhing well to the ſoules of all my Fellow Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Siſters, Fellow heires of the ſame Kingdome with me, that they would not take up things lightly and ſlightly, but labour to gett inward principles in their owne ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:7774:3"/>And to gett a ground and bottome for their owne ſpirits, for theſe things they profeſſe and hold, that ſo they may not build upon the ſand, but upon the unmoveable Rock, the Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> that ſhall never be ſhaken, that ſo they may, though all the power of darkneſſe ſet themſelves againſt them, yet that they may cleave cloſe to God, &amp; our Saviour Chriſt, and the purity of his Goſpell, for we muſt looke for fanning and ſifting, and for the fiery tryall; therefore let us ſit downe and reckon, what it will coſt us, and if we be not willing to loſe all for his ſake, yea and to hate all even Father and Mother, riches &amp; life, &amp;c. if they ſtand in our way to keep us from him, we are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of him. <hi>Math.</hi> 10.37. and 16.24. <hi>Mark.</hi> 8 34. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.23.24. and 14.26.27.</p>
            <p>And for my owne part, the Lord himſelfe hath ſo firmly by his owne enlightening Spirit ſo fully convinced me, and ſetled my ſoule ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveably in his truth, that I aſſuredly know, that all the power in Earth, yea and the gates of Hell it ſelfe ſhall never be able to move me or prevaile againſt me, for the Lord who is the worker of all my workes in me and for me, hath founded and built me upon that ſure &amp; unmoveable foundation the Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and I know if ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand deaths for my conſcience and the cauſe of my God, (for which with courage and rejoycing I now beare witneſſe to, and am cloſe priſoner in bonds, lying day and night in Fetters of Jron, both hands &amp; legges) ſhould be inflicted upon me, I ſhould ſing, rejoyce &amp; triumph in them all; For my God makes me glory in my tribulation, and my ſoule is filled ſo full of that ſweetneſſe and joy, that it findes in my God alone that my tongue and penne is never able to the full to expreſſe &amp; utter it, (to his praiſe I deſire to ſpeake it,) and I doe beleeve, that it is not poſſible for any man in any condition whatſoever (whoſe neck in the beſt doth ſtoope to the yoake of Antichriſt) to have his heart and ſpirit elevated and lifted up above it ſelfe in that high degree, with ſpirituall joy and comfort, divine and heavenly ſtrength and ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that mine is, for the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, they have no reſt night nor day who worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, and whoſoever recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the marke of his name; And I doe beleeve it to be true, as I am able to ſpeake by my owne experience; For they may have ſome ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of reſt and peace, and ſudden Flaſhes of joy and comfort, but when a ſtorme or Tempeſt doth ariſe, they are ſo poſſeſſed, with baſe and cowardly feare and diſtraction of ſpirit, that they are like men without hearts, and are ready to runne into every hole, to hide their heads from the face of man, a poore worme, being ready to ſay (when a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt ariſeth) with them in the 6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.17. Let the Mountaine and Rock fall on us, and hide us from the face of him that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb, for the great day of his wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand; When as on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7774:4"/>
the Righteous is as bold as a Lyon, though the wicked fly when none perſueth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.1. &amp; 18.10. The name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower, the Righteous runneth unto it and are ſafe.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91. he that dwelleth in the ſecret place of the moſt high, ſhall abide under the ſhaddow of the Almighty, and he ſhall be ſafe from the feare of all danger, as the Holy Ghoſt there doth declare; So that we ſee the feare and terrour that poſſeſſeth the hearts and ſpirits of all thoſe whoſe necks are either in part or in whole under the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall yoake and bondage of the Beaſt; And alſo the reſt and peace, and holy ſecurity that they are in that ſubmitt alone to the Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> for their ſpirituall Lord and King; And are willing to follow him, wherſoever he goes, not loving their ſoules to the death, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. but keepe cloſe and hold faſt the name and faith of Chriſt, even where Satan hath his Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.13. for he hath ſaid and promiſed unto his people that keepe cloſe to him, becauſe thou haſt kept the word of my patience; I will alſo keepe thee from the houre of Temptation, which ſhall come upon all the World, to try them that dwell upon the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.10. And this have I found by experience, ſince the Lord in great mercy and rich loving kindneſſe, by his ſtrength and power inabled me to withdraw my ſoule totally and finally from the greateſt ſpirituall yoake and bondage, that ever any mortall man groaned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, namely the ſpirituall yoake and bondage of the Beaſt, or Roman State, unto which, whoſoever is hated of the Lord, and doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto him, doe ſubmitt &amp; yeeld, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.4. and 12.7.9. &amp; 13.8. But the Lord from all eternity hath loved me with his everlaſting love, hath delivered my ſoule from it, and ſet me at liberty, and in a large place, and hath given me reſt and eaſe, and hath put a ſong of prayer and thankſgiving into my mouth, unto the Lord of glory and the Lamb that ſitts upon his Throne, who is bleſſed for ever and ever, and my God hath filled my ſoule ſo full of Heavenly matter, that had I but a current vent, I could <hi>ex tempore</hi> write an hundred Sheetes of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to you, filled full of Heavenly expreſſions of the Lords goodneſſe, faithfulneſſe, loving kindneſſe and Truth, for my ſoule is ravished with that fulneſſe, ſweetneſſe, aimeableneſſe, and beautifulneſſe, that I finde in my God; Oh that my ſoule were altogether with him, that I might be ſatisfyed with his fulneſſe, and might ſolace my ſoule face to face, which I moſt confidently know I ſhall in his due time; But, Oh I ſay againe and againe, that J were with him, for he hath crucifyed the World, and all things here below unto me, and hath enabled me to account and eſteeme all things beſides himſelfe, as dung and durt, not being worthy of caſting any affectionate eye upon them, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.8.9. and he hath pitched my ſoule upon himſelfe, as a naked and a ſingle object, in whom alone the quinteſſence of delight, beautie, and ſatiſfaction is to be had, enjoyed, and poſſeſſed, and for my ſhackled
<pb facs="tcp:7774:4"/>
condition that I am in, it is moſt ſweete and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I am as merry, yea more chearefull, then ever I was in any condition in my life, and can ſleepe as ſoundly in my Boots and Irons, as <hi>Peter</hi> did betweene the two Souldiers, when he was in priſon, who when the Angell of the Lord came to him, to deliver him; He was faine to ſmite him, before he awaked, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.6.7. And I doe ſing <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> and J am as merry as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Sylas</hi> were, when they were in the Stocks, and in priſon, who ſung Pſalmes and Prayſes at midnight, ſo that the Priſoners heard them, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.24.25. for the Lord hath ſo ſtrengthened me with divine power and ſtrength, for the Lord of Hoſts is my confidence; And in the Lord <hi>Iehovah</hi> there is everlaſting ſtrength; And there is no torments, that the greateſt Tyrans in the World can inflict upon me, that can make me miſerable, ſad, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, for I know all my torments make but way for a greater degree of glory, which I am confident one day I ſhall be poſſeſſour off, and J long with <hi>Paul</hi> to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt, not out of any trouble or burdenſomeneſſe, that I finde or ſee in my preſent afflicted diſtreſſed condition, (according to the fleſh) but to me it is ſweete and joyfull in the Lord, and I know when the Lord hath fully tried me, and done his good pleaſure with me, and by me, I ſhall come out of the Furnace purified and clenſed from my droſſe filth and corruption, <hi>Iob</hi> 23. for the Lord already in part hath refined me, but not with Silver, for he hath choſen me in the furnace of affliction, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 48.10.</p>
            <p>This by way of <hi>Preface</hi> or <hi>Apology</hi> for my ſelfe; And now J come to the matter.</p>
            <p>And for my owne judgement, it beeing matter concerning the glory and prayſe of my God, although I know it will be very unpleaſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pallets of many, yea of my neare and deare freinds, from whom I have received expreſſions of love and kindneſſe, whoſe loving affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it may be, may be turned to a diſtaſt to my perſon, and my ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, which if it bee, J ſhall patiently beare it, for the ſincerity of my heart is knowne unto God, who is the ſearcher of the heart, and the tryer of the reines, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.23. <hi>Ier.</hi> 11.20. and 17.10. And I will call him to record, and to beare witneſſe, that the glory of his great and holy name, is the ſingle object of all my actions, undertakings, and proceedings; And if I ſhall incurre hatred therefore from my freinds, J ſhall comfort my ſelfe with that which my ſaviour hath ſaid, which is that he came not to ſend peace on Earth, but a ſword, for I am (ſaith he) to ſet a man at variance againſt his Father, and the daughter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her Mother, and the daughter in Law againſt her Mother in Law, <hi>Math.</hi> 10.34.35. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.49.51.53. and with that which <hi>Paul</hi> comforted himſelfe with, if he could approve his heart to God, he did not care what man ſaid of him, for ſaith he, doe J ſeeke, to pleaſe men,
<pb facs="tcp:7774:5"/>
for if J yet pleaſe men, I ſhould not be the ſervant of Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10.</p>
            <p>But now for my judgement, for my owne part, if I ſhould never heare a Sermon while I live, yet I ſhould never dare to heare one from any man, good or bad, that is made a Miniſter by the Prelates, or any of their Creatures, or by vertue of any of their muddy Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Lawes, neither dare I have any ſpirituall communion with them; ſo long as they ſtand in their calling, in regard I am perſwaded that he that heareth them ſinneth, having no warrant out of the booke of God to doe it, and by undenyable conſequence I will prove it, that whoſoever heares them ſo long as they Officiat by vertue of their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and power, which they have received from the Biſhops, to preach, doth heare the Devill; for the Holy Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13 4. the ſubjects of the Kingdome of the Beaſt worſhipped the Dragon, (that is to ſay the Devill, which gave power unto the Beaſt, and they worſhipped the Beaſt, ſaying, who is like to the Beaſt, who is able to warre with the Beaſt.</p>
            <p>Now, let us not thinke that they did fall downe to the Devil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and doe homage to him, face to face, for we never reade of any that did this, but the Holy Ghoſt doth here declare, that all thoſe that ſtoope or yeeld in the leaſt to the Lawes of the Beaſt doth worſhip &amp; ſerve the Devill, from whom he hath received his power.</p>
            <p>But all the Miniſters doe ſtoope unto is Lawes, which none of them are able to deny, there o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e they are as really his ſervants and ſubjects, all the time they doe ſo a they can be.</p>
            <p>And we have no ground out of the Scripture to judge better of them;</p>
            <p>As they are not the ſubjects and ſervants of Chriſt, that intyrely doe not ſtoope unto his Lawes and Scepte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; For is he, or can he be ſaid to be a ſubject to the King of England, that ſtoopes, ſubmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts, &amp; yeelds to the Lawes and Scepter of any other King, his greateſt and profeſſedſt enemy upon the Earth.</p>
            <p>No, without doubt; But they doe ſtoope to the Lawes of Antichriſts Kingdome, who is the greateſt and profeſſedſt enemy that ever <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> had in the World, as I will be ready to prove to the faces of the beſt of them in any publick diſputa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion.</p>
            <p>Therefore they are reall and truely his ſervants; for his ſervant you are to whom you obey.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> ſaith to his Diſciples, he that heares you, heareth me, and he that heareth me heareth him that ſent me.</p>
            <p>So on the contrary, he that heares the Miniſters, heares the Prelates that made and ſent them. And he that heares the Prelates, heares the Pope, that authoriſed &amp; gave them their authority; And he that heares the Pope, heares the Devill, that gave him his power; So that I ſay we
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7774:5"/>
can not partake with them in hearing, or in any adminiſtrations of Gods ſacred things, but we muſt of neceſſity partake of their calling and inſtitution, by vertue of which they officiat and adminiſter; And that J prove from <hi>Pauls</hi> words in the firſt of the <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.18. <hi>Are not they which eate of the Sacrifice partakers of the Altar;</hi> Even ſo I ſay, are not they which partake of their adminiſtration, partakers of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution? Yea without doubt or queſtion. Now, for their inſtitution, it is not from God (as J will maintaine againſt them all) therefore we are not to heare them, nor in the leaſt to partake with them or their adminiſtration.</p>
            <p>And for your better ſatiſfaction ſeriouſly reade and weigh the 10. of <hi>Iohn:</hi> And to me it ſeemes ſo cleare and plaine, that I doe not doubt but that we are not to heare any Miniſters but thoſe that are made by vertue of the Lawes and power of Chriſt, which he hath left to his Church, in his laſt will and Teſtament, which Lawes are unalterable and unchangeable to the end of the World, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.3. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.13. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 13.14.15.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.1.2.6. <hi>Math.</hi> 28.19.20.</p>
            <p>But they are not made by vertue of the Lawes and power of Chriſt, but by the Lawes and Authority of Antichriſt, and therefore we are not to heare them, for ſaith Chriſt, my Sheepe heare my voice, &amp; I know them, and they follow me, and a ſtranger they will not follow, but will fly from him, for they know not the voice of ſtrangers; Here you ſee Chriſt layes it downe, as a ſigne and a marke to know his Sheepe by, that they will not heare, nor give eare to falſe Shepheards.</p>
            <p>But ſo are all the Miniſters, for they come not in by the dore, but by a falſe power and Authority; namely, by the power of the man of ſinne, Chriſts implacable enemy.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is not Lawfull for any of Gods people, to heare them; For when the Prelates by vertue of his power, bids them, and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize them to preach, they doe preach; And when they command them to hold their peace, they are ſilent, and let their flock runne at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, when as a good and true Shepheard layeth downe his life for his Sheepheard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But many object and ſay, it is true, that their calling as it comes from the Prelates, is unlawfull, but they have an inward cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, for they are fitted for the worke of the Miniſterie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which J anſwer and ſay, I reade of no inward calling, that any of thoſe Officers had, that Chriſt or his Apoſtles did inſtitute in the New Teſtament, for the Apoſtles had their calling from Chriſt, and the other Officers had their calling from the Churches, where they themſelves were members, and over which, by the Lawes and power of Chriſt, they were made Officers.</p>
            <p>But if the Miniſters of Antichriſt have an inward calling, I deſire to ſee it proved by the Scripture; And as for their qualifications and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eneſſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7774:6"/>
for the Miniſtrie. J deny, and ſay, that they are not qualified according to the command of Chriſt, by <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> &amp; <hi>Titus;</hi> And I doe affirme and will maintaine it, that no man ought to be Elected for the worke of the Miniſtrie, unleſſe he have all thoſe quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications that is by the Holy Ghoſt ſet downe in the 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and the firſt of <hi>Titus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, there is none of them, yea the beſt among them, that hath the qualification for a Biſhop, a Paſtor, or an Elder, which is all. One muſt not be a Novice, leaſt being lifted up with pride, he fall into the condemnation of the Devill. Alſo he muſt hold faſt the faithfull word as it hath been taught, that he may be able by ſound Doctrine, both to exhort and convince the gaineſayers; But none of them have either of theſe, for they are ſo farre from being able to convince gaineſayers by ſound Doctrine, that they are but novices in many things, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wilfully or ignorantly are blinde of the naked wayes of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing darkned with the ſmoake which came out of the bottomleſſe pitt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.2, and J will juſtify it to the faces of the beſt of them, that they are enemies to the Kingly Office of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and the right govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Church, both in practiſe and in judgement; and therefore are not fit (take them at the beſt) to be Paſtors over Chriſts Sheepe; Neither can any of them ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. That he was cleare of the blood of all men, in that he ceaſed not to declare unto them, the whole Counſell of God, which every faithfull Paſtor ought to doe; but none of them have done it, nor are able, for as I ſaid before, they are ignorant, of it, and are enemies to it, as they doe witneſſe in their Pulpits, where they preach againſt the naked and pure wayes of God, and the Profeſſours of it, but none of them dare to enter the liſt of a Publick ſet diſpute.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> I but ſay others they preach the Word of God, and that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be corrupted by their calling, but remaine the Word of God ſtill, therefore we may Lawfully heare it from them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwet, they preach the outſide of the Word, it is true, but the marrow and pith of it, they meddle but little with, for the beſt of them are yet ignorant of the marrow, of many choice Truths of God, for their underſtandings are ſo overſpred with the Foggie Miſts of the darke and black Kingdome of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> that they want ſpirituall eyes to ſee it; And behold it untill the Lord in mercy if ſo he pleaſe to open their eyes; And what though they doe preach the Word, they have no authority from God ſo to doe, if they have, let them ſtand up and ſhow it, and prove it; Not with human learning, but by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Scripture.</p>
            <p>It is true, the Devill himſelfe preached Chriſt, and made a glorious confeſſion of him, ſaying: <hi>I know that thou art Ieſus the Chriſt, the Son of God, Mark</hi> 1.24.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:7774:6"/>This if it had come from one of Chriſts owne ſervants, it had been moſt acceptable, and well pleaſing to him, but in regard it comes from the Devill, he will not owne it, but commands him to hold his peace.</p>
            <p>It is very true, the Word of God is good and ſweete, and a comfort to the ſoules of his ſervants, if it be preached by any that hath autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from Chriſt, we are bound to heare it; But the beſt of the Miniſters have no authority or warrant from Chriſt to preach the Word, nor we to heare it from them, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 10.2.3.5. <hi>Hoſes</hi> 9.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16.</p>
            <p>But to the wicked ſaith God, <hi>What haſt thou to doe to declare my Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, or that thou ſhouldeſt take my Covenant in thy mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, looke upon all of them to be ſuch as God here ſpeakes off, in regard of their inſtitution and ſtanding, being viſible members of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts Kingdome; I doe not, nor will not meddle with their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, nor no mans elſe, but only with their ſinfull and wicked ſtation and ſtanding; Which as I am a ſubject to Chriſts Kingdome, and a priſoner in bonds and fetters of Iron, for his cauſe, I am bound in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience for to doe it, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5 23. <hi>Curſe ye Meroz</hi> (ſaith the Angell of the Lord) <hi>yea curſe ye bitterly the inhabitants therein, becauſe they came not forth, to the helpe of the Lord againſt the mighty</hi> Yea the Spirit of God ſaith; That they are bleſſed and happy that takes Babels Bratts, and daſh them againſt the ſtones, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.8.9.</p>
            <p>But they are all Sonnes and Children of Spirituall Babell or Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8. and 14.8 and 18.2.</p>
            <p>Now, by vertue of their being members of his Kingdome, we have no ground or warrant out of the Word of God, to heare them, for it is impoſſible to be a ſervant and a ſubject both to Chriſt and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt; But they are ſubjects to Antichriſts Kingdome; Therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid truely to be ſubjects and ſervants to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For is not he properly a ſubject to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> that ſubmits to his Lawes, and beares Office under him, by vertue of his authoritie; And can ſuch men, while they doe ſo; be ſaid and truely to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be ſubjects to the King of England, unto whoſe Lawes they doe not ſubmit; Without doubt they cannot. Even ſo can the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters or Preiſts (for ſo is their inſtitution) who ſubmit unto the Lawes of Antichriſt, and beare Office under him, and execute their Office by vertue of his power and Authoritie, and therefore are his Servants and Subjects, and cannot truely be ſaid to be the Servants and Subjects of Chriſt, unto whoſe Lawes they doe not ſubmit.</p>
            <p>Therefore we are not to heare them, or to have any thing to doe with them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:7774:7"/>Againe, <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> that is to ſay, the Church of God is the place which God hath choſen, and hath promiſed his preſence and bleſſing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.13.14.15. and 88.17. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. Now, I would know where any of his people hath any warrant to ſeeke his preſence and bleſſing any where but where he hath promiſed it; But he never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed it in the viſible Aſſemblies of Antichriſts Kingdome; Therefore we have no ground or warrant to ſeeke it there, or come there at all; Much more concerning this I have and am able to ſay, but I am above meaſure ſtraightned, for want of a fitting opportunitie; And therefore for your further ſatiſfaction, repaire to the peruſall of a little thing, called a declaration, where the people of God are to ſeeke his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and bleſſing, only in <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> the Citty and Church of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46 4. and 48.1.2.8. <hi>Eſay</hi> 60.14. and 62.11.12 and not in the Aſſemblies of Antichriſt, being Cages of uncleane Birds, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18 2. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 13.21.22.</p>
            <p>Againe, I ſee no ground or warrant, that any of Gods people have, to have any ſpiritual communion with them, in regard God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his people, at all times, very ſtrictly, that they ſhall have no communion with Idolaters, nor their Idols, as the whole Booke of God doth declare; and I deſire you to read the <hi>ſeventh of Deut:</hi> and there you ſhall ſee Gods ſtrict command to that end. But the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters all of them are Idolaters, yea Idols themſelves; Therefore we muſt have no communion with them. Now, that they are Jdolaters, is as cleare as the Sun, that ſhines at noone-day; And that they are Idols, I am able to prove it to their faces, For an Idoll is nothing elſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scripture but a Creature or Creatures ſet a part, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted to worſhip God with or by, which he himſelfe never ordained for that end and purpoſe; But ſuch are all the Prelates Miniſters, for they were never of his ordaining or inſtituting, but of his greateſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the Pillars of Antichriſts Kingdome, by vertue of whoſe power they officiate. Therefore they are Idols, whom all Gods people, that are faithfull Souldiers and leige Subjects, ought to be a meanes, and a helpe, to roote up and pull downe.</p>
            <p>Now, this definition of an Idoll is not only according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but is given by the foundeſt Nonconformiſts themſelves, as you may read in their Bookes, where they have ſtrongly proved the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice, and the Croſſe in <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and kneeling in the Act o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> receiving the Communion; And the reſt of the Prelates inſtituted ſacred Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, as they call them, ſaying in their Reaſons before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer, for the retaining of ſome Ceremonies, and the aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of others, that they are apt to ſtirr up the dull minde of man, to the remembrance of ſome duty to God, by ſome ſpeciall ſignification, whereby he might be edi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:7774:7"/>Now, if you reade the <hi>Scots Diſpute,</hi> which was printed at <hi>Leyden,</hi> in Holland, the laſt Summer, you ſhall there find ſtrong reaſons, to prove the Ceremonies Idols; and his maine Argument is, becauſe they are not of Gods inſtitution, but of ſinfull mans ordaining.</p>
            <p>Alſo that No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le and worthy Doctor (whom I ſo much honour and reſpect) <hi>Doctor Baſtwicke</hi> in his Booke, called <hi>The Vanity and Impiety of the old Lettany,</hi> doth prove it to be an Idoll, yea and calls it a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſoule-murthering Jdoll; And that upon the ſame ground, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not of Gods us of mans inſtitution, without any ground or war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant from God; and there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore is an Idoll, and is to be deteſted as an abominable Idoll. Now, what they ſay of the Ceremonies, and of the Service, the ſame I ſay o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Prelates, and all the Miniſters that are made by them and have their calling from the Biſhops, they are Creatures ſet a part to worſhip God with or by, but were never of his inſtituting, or by vertue o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his power, but by mans inſtitution, and by vertue of the power of the greateſt enemy that ever <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> had, or his Kingdome ever had on Earth, namely <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> or the Kingdome of the Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9 3.7.10.11. and 13.6.7.16.17. and 12 6.7.15.17.</p>
            <p>And therefore they are Idols, whom ſo long as they ſtand in their places and callings under the ſpirituall Antichriſtian authority, which they all ſubmit to and ſubject themſelves to, I ſhall not dare to have any ſpirituall communion with them, either in publicke or private, for what fellowſhip hath righteouſneſſe with unrighteouſneſſe; Or what communion hath light with darkneſſe; And what Concord hath Chriſt with <hi>Beliall?</hi> Or what part hath he that beleeveth with an Infidell? Or what agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols? Surely, none at all. Wherefore come you out from among them, and be you ſeperate, ſaith the Lord, and touch no uncleane thing, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you, and will be a Father unto you, and you ſhall be my Sonnes and Daughters, ſaith the Lord Almighty, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14 to the end. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 62.11. <hi>Ier.</hi> 51.6 7 <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4 5.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, though J am, and doe reſpect them as men, being the Creatures of God, and doe reverence them as they are privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, and Head-members of the State; though it be not ſutable in the leaſt to their falſe pretended ſpirituall calling. But as they are Biſhops and Officers in the Kingdome of the Beaſt, my knee and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and reverence, ſhall by the ſtrength of my God, be as litle to them, as <hi>Mordecay</hi> was to proud <hi>Haman,</hi> who was King <hi>Abaſhueros,</hi> Cheife Favorite, being above all the Princes that were with him, <hi>Heſt.</hi> 3.1. Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mordecay</hi> would not ſo much as bow to him, or doe him any reverence, <hi>verſe the</hi> 3. though it doe procure me as much wrath from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as it did <hi>Mordecay</hi> from <hi>Haman</hi> of whom the Holy Goſt ſaith he was full of wrath, ſeeing <hi>Mordecay</hi> would not reverence him, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5.6.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7774:8"/>
Neither will I ever give baile to them, or part with any money, either to them or any of their Creatures, for any thing whatſoever, unleſſe it be meerely for Temporall and Earthly things, in regard I doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it is the duty of all Gods people, who deſire to glorify him in their lives and converſations, and to ſhine as ſo many burning Lamps in the midſt of a peruerſe and crooked generation, as they ought and ſhould doe; Neither to bow finger, knee, or hatt unto any of them, or to doe them any reverence, as they are Biſhops and Cheife Pillars in the Kingdome of Antichriſt, for by vertue of their calling and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, they are the deadly and implacable enemies of God, and are ſo many pernicious and damnable Idols (by which God is exceedingly diſhonoured) ſet up by the Devill in the Kingdome of the Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9 3 and 13.2.4. and 16.13.14. And I can prove it, that it was as Lawfull for the 3 Children, to worſhip or bow to <hi>Nebuchadnezars</hi> Idoll, as for Gods people to bow and doe homage to them.</p>
            <p>And for my owne part, if they require of me any ſuch, my anſwer ſhall be to them, as the 3 Children was to the King. <hi>Dan</hi> 3.16.17.18. Be it knowne to you Biſhops and Doctors, I feare you not; or the God whom I ſerve and feare, is able to deliver me out of your hands, and from your Tyranniſing crueltie; But if he doe not, be it knowne unto you, Oh ye Prelates, that I will not ſerve you, nor worſhip you, nor yeeld nor ſubmit in any ſpirituall things unto you; And if I were at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, I would profeſſe thoſe Truths of God ſurely without feare, which he himſelfe hath made knowne unto me; And if J were at any time taken by any of their Officers, I would not goe to priſon with them, unleſſe they carried me by force; Yet if it were the meaneſt Officer in the Kingdome that tooke me, that were made an Officer by vertue of the Kings Authority and power, I would ſubmit unto him, and goe with him, whether he would have me, for I know the Kings Authority is from God; And if I ſhould diſobey it, I ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey God, and ſinne againſt God, and breake his Command, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. And therefore I will obey him, his Lawes, and all thoſe that beare his Authority, in all things they command or enjoyne me; without any the leaſt reſiſtance at all, heartily from my heart, either actively or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively; for if they command me any thing that is not contrary to the Word of God, I will obey them actively; But if they command me any thing that is diſhonourable to God or his Truth, I dare not in the leaſt obey them actively, but ſay with the Apoſtle, whether it be fitt to obey God or Men, judge ye, for we ought to obey God rather then Men, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.29. Yet I will ſubmit my body to them, and ſuffer cheerfully, without any grudging any thing they ſhall inflict upon me, for I doe hold it unlawfull for any of Gods people, in their greateſt Oppreſſion by the Majeſtrate, to rebell or to take up any Temporal armes againſt them, whether the Oppreſſion be in Spirituall or Temporall things,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7774:8"/>
but only to pray and make uſe of Gods two edged Sword, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.15. and waite upon with patience for redreſſe and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and to ſeeke unto him for ſtrength, that they may willingly and couragiouſly ſuffer any Terrours or Torments that they will inflict up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, for ſtanding cloſe to God, and his naked Truth and cauſe.</p>
            <p>But to the Kingdome of the Beaſt, theſe members of which the Prelates are, will I never ſtoope by the might of the Lord of Hoſts, nor have any ſpirituall communion with them, for the Lord hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly commanded me and all his people to have nothing to doe with Idols, nor with Idolaters, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.14. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.21. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.32. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.1.2.3.4.5. and 12.3. Now, they are the greateſt Idolaters that euer were in rhe world, and the moſt pernitious Idols, that are upon the Earth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.20. &amp; cap: 17. for they haue a golden Cup put in their hands, it is full of abomination &amp; filthines, &amp; with it they dazle the eyes of the world, &amp; make it to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit cloſe &amp; hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fornication, &amp; Idolatrie, which is the greateſt and moſt dangerous Idolatrie that is, for they couer their wickedneſſe and deceiveableneſſe over with the Name of the Lamb, but for all that doe the deeds of the Dragon. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.11. <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.44. But if they profeſſed Idolatry openly to the eyes of the World, the people would deteſt them, but they doe it cloſely and covertly, and therefore are not ſo eaſily diſcerned, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive very many, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.5. And therefore the Beaſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is called, as it is indeed, the Miſterie of iniquitie, 2 <hi>Theſſ</hi> 2.7.</p>
            <p>Now, J will maintaine it, that the Kingdome of the Beaſt is the greateſt Idol that ever was in the World, and the greateſt plague that ever God ſent into the World, as the <hi>Revelation of Saint Iohn</hi> doth declare, and as appeares by the expreſſions of the Spirit of God, in the 8. Chapter, where we may read, that when the 4. Firſt Angels had ſounded their Trumpets, mighty and horrible plagues then followed them, worſe and more great were to come after, as appeares by the vehement expreſſions and calling out of the Holy Ghoſt, with a loud voice, <hi>Verſe the laſt;</hi> Saying, <hi>Woe, Woe, Woe to the inhabitants of the Earth</hi> (reitterating 3 times together) <hi>by reaſon of the other voices of the Trumpet of the three Angels which are yet to ſound.</hi> For why the fifth Angell in the firſt Verſe of the next Chapter ſounded, then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed a mighty &amp; horrible plague to all the inhabitants of the world; The like whereof was never heard off before, and that is the ſmoake that came out of the bottomleſſe pitt, which was that horrible darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſpirituall blindneſſe and ſottiſh ignorance that ſeazed upon the World, dureing the time of the Beaſts Kingdome, which was ſo great, that the viſible face of a Church of Chriſt could not be found upon the Earth, for the heavens departed as a ſcroll together, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.14.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:7774:9"/>And out of this ſmoake or darkneſſe came the Locuſts the beaſts officers or Clergy, which are a multitude in number, there being in the Kingdome of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> at this day above an hundred ſeverall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers; Whereas in the Kingdome of Chriſt there is but 5. Namely, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, Teacher, Elder, Deacon, and Widdow, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.7.1. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.2. and 5. <hi>Titus</hi> 1.5.7.</p>
            <p>Againe, the Spirit of God pronounceth another woe to the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Earth and of the Sea, for the Devill is turned downe unto you, having great wrath, becauſe he knoweth that he hath but a ſhort time, the like expreſſion we read not of in the whole Booke of God, nor that there were any ſuch plagues ſince the beginning of the World; As thoſe were which came along with the Kingdome of the Roman Beaſt, as the Stories of all ages, ſince his beginning, is able to witneſſe and prove, for men worſhipped the Devill, and committed ſuch horrible wickedneſſe, for which God ſent ſuch mighty plagues upon them, as the like before was never heard off before in the world, as the whole <hi>Booke of the Revelation</hi> doth witneſſe; Therefore of all Idols that ever were in the World, Gods people have moſt cauſe of all to deteſt, abhorre, and abominate the Idolaters and the Idols in the Kingdom of the Beaſt, &amp; whoſoever the Lord loves he will deliver fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. But thoſe that are his enemies, and hated of him, ſhall continue in ſubjection to it <hi>Rev</hi> 9.4. and 13.8. and 14.9.10.11. and 19.20. <hi>Pro.</hi> 2.18.19. and 5.5. and 7.27. and 9.18.</p>
            <p>Now, the time of the raigne and durance of the Kingdome of the Beaſt, in the 11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. is ſaid to be 42 moneths; and in the 12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. it is called a time times and halfe a time, which is three yeares and a halfe; And in the firſt Verſe of this Chapter, it is tearmed to be 1260 dayes, which is juſt 42 moneths, reckoning 30 dayes to every moneth, and it makes alſo three yeares and a halfe, accounting 12 Moneths to every yeare; and this is the time of the Raigne of the Beaſt, or the durance of Antichriſts Kingdome; Which if we reckon each day for a yeare, as the Lord himſelfe in Scripture doth, as we may read when the Spies that went from the Tents of Iſraell, at the Lords command, to ſearch the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which they were a doing 40 dayes; And at their returne they gave out an evill report of it, which made the people to ſinne and rebell againſt God, and not to give credit to his word, Oath and promiſe, which was to bring them into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> to give it to them, notwithſtanding the greatneſſe and poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Heathen, for the Lord himſelfe had promiſed to caſt them out, but becauſe they beleeved him not, but rebelled againſt him, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſtrength and power of the Heathen, the Lord would make them to wander in the barren and deſart Wilderneſſe 40 yeares. For ſaith he, after the number of the dayes, in which ye ſearched the Land even 40 dayes, each day for a yeare, ſhall you beare your iniquities,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7774:9"/>
even 40 yeares, and you ſhall know my breach of promiſe, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.34. <hi>Ezek:</hi> 4.5.6. where God ſaith thus to the Prophet: J have laid upon thee the yeares of iniquity, according to the number of the dayes, three hundred and ninety dayes, ſo ſhalt thou beare the iniquity of the Houſe of Iſrael; and when thou haſt accompliſhed them, lye againe on thy right ſide, and thou ſhalt beare the iniquity of the houſe of <hi>Iudah</hi> 40 dayes, I have appointed each day for a yeare. So that if we expound the 1260. by theſe 2 places of ſcripture, reckning as God him ſelf doth each day for a yeare; which I verily beleeve is the right mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Holy Ghoſt; We ſhall finde that the Beaſts Kingdome ſhall endure from the beginning to the end 1260. yeares; For I ſee no ground that theſe places ſhould be expounded litterally for three yeares and a halfe, and no more, for it is impoſſible that Antichriſt ſhould doe all theſe ſtrange things, in ſo ſhort a time, that is ſaid, he he ſhall doe &amp; fulfill, therefore without doubt it muſt be expounded each day for a yeare, for the man of ſinne was a working in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time, but the Emperour who letted him, kept him out of his ſeate till he was taken away, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. Now, during the time of Antichriſt, the Holy Cittie, or the true Church of God, is to be troden under foote, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. and to be in a ſad and afflicted condition, and to be perſecuted by the beaſt, and the members of his ſtate &amp; King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome all that time, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7.15. and Chapt. 12. though now and then ſhe ſhould have ſome breathing and refreſhing times; And when An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts Kingdome growes to an end, (which bleſſed be God doth ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten apace,) the Foggie Miſts of darkeneſſe, blindneſſe and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, which is <hi>the ſmoake</hi> that the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, <hi>came out of the bottomleſse pitt; Rev.</hi> 9. ſhall in ſome meaſure be diſpeld, and the Beames of Truth and ſpirituall light, ſhall breake and ſhine out, as is plaine in the 10.14, and 16. Chapters; for then the Booke of Life the Holy Scripture is opened, which in former ages lay altogether hid, and in a manner ſhutt up in obſcurity &amp; darkneſſe, as appeares plainly out of the 11. Chapt. Therefore let us not wonder, nor think it ſtrange that the eyes of ſpirituall underſtanding, (which is to know, ſee &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the naked Truths of God,) is opened of ſo few of the great and famous men, in the eye of the World, but continue ſtill enemies to the bare &amp; naked Truths of God, for the Kingdome of the Beaſt is not yet deſtroyed, &amp; the ſmoake of the bottomleſſe pitt hath ſo darkened the Sunne &amp; the aire, that the ſpirituall eyes of few mens underſtandings, are opened to ſee &amp; take notice of the intyre Truths of God; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding let us take heede, that we be not offended &amp; ſtumble to our deſtruction; <hi>Luke.</hi> 20.17.18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. at the naked wayes and cleare and pure Truth of Chriſt, becauſe they are but few and meane in the eſtimation of the World, that doth imbrace them and profeſſe them, for the Church of <hi>Smirna,</hi> though ſhee were but poore and meane in the eye of the World, yet ſhee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7774:10"/>
was rich in Gods account, becauſe ſhe kept cloſe to his naked wayes and Truths, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.9. whereas on the contrary <hi>proud and haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Laodicea,</hi> who was full of outward riches and treaſures; And wanted nothing that might make her gliſter &amp; ſhine in the eyes of the world, yet notwithſtanding is odious in the ſight of God, becauſe ſhe was <hi>luke warme</hi> and neither <hi>hot</hi> nor <hi>cold,</hi> for he threatens to <hi>ſpew her out of his mouth;</hi> doe you your ſelfe make the application; Likewiſe let us take notice of that thankſgiving, which Chriſt gives to his Father: J thanke thee oh Father, Lord of Heaven and Earth, becauſe thou haſt hidd theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revealed them to Babes, even ſo Father, for ſo it ſeemed good in thy ſight, <hi>Math.</hi> 11.25.26.</p>
            <p>The naked purity and Truth of the Goſpell of Chriſt, is too homely a thing, for the great learned Doctors of the world, to imbrace, ſtoope and ſubmitt unto; for Chriſt hath ſaid, that the profeſſors of it ſhall be hated of all men, yea of their parents, kindred, and Freinds, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.16.17. <hi>Marke</hi> 13.12. and are accounted as Sheepe to the ſlaughter, all the day, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. whoſe condition is to be afflicted and perſecuted here by the men of the world, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.18.19, and 16.2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.33. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.4.6.7.8. for there muſt and will be to the end of the World en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity betweene the ſeede of the woman and the ſeede of the Serpent, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. and therefore falſe Teachers and ſeducers, though they come in the name of Chriſt, and preach part of his Goſpell <hi>Math.</hi> 7.5, and 24.5. yet they are enemies to Chriſt, the purity of his Truth and people, though they make a flowriſhing ſhow in the fleſh, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they love not the Croſſe of Chriſt, which alwaies goes alonge, and is inſeperable from the zealous and ſtrict profeſſion of him and his Truth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.11.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.19. nor will they part with their eaſe pleaſure and fatt morſels, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 65.10, 11, 12, nor <hi>ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution with the people of God,</hi> for the Truth of God, as Moſes did, <hi>Heb:</hi> 11: 25. Therefore they will neither imbrace the purity of the Truth, nor willingly let thoſe that would, <hi>Gal:</hi> 6: 12. Yet for all that though they will not, yet all thoſe that deſire to approve their hearts and ſpirits unto God, and to glorifie him both in their lives &amp; deaths, muſt not forſake his Truth, for feare of perſecution, or loſing of their kindred, or Freinds, <hi>Gal:</hi> 5: 11: <hi>Math:</hi> 10:33: <hi>Marke</hi> 8: 34: 38: <hi>Luke</hi> 14: 26: for here Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, that he that loveth Father or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or his owne life, or any thing elſe more then him, ſhall never poſſeſſe nor enjoy him, neither here nor hereafter; For he ſaith: He that denies him or his Truth before men, him will he denie before his Father which is in Heaven. Therefore in regard the Goſpell of Chriſt, in the ſtrict profeſſion of it, is ſo meane, contemptible and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome a thing in the blinde and darke eyes of the World, and lyes under the reproach and ignominy of the men thereof, the great
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7774:10"/>
Rabbies doe ſtumble at it, and doe not imbrace it, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1: 19: 20, for it is written ſaith God, <hi>I will deſtroy the wiſdome of the wiſe, and wil bring to nought the vnderſtandings of the prudent, where is the wiſe, where is the ſcribe, where is the diſputer of this world: hath not God made fooliſh the wiſdome of this world Iſa:</hi> 29.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 33, 18. <hi>Oba: verſe</hi> 8. Therefore in regard the great Doctors of the world doe not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the ways of God: the multitude ſtumble at them, likewiſe, being ready to ſay with them <hi>Io:</hi> 7, <hi>haue any of the Rulers or of the Phariſes beleeued on him, but this people who knoweth not the law &amp; are accurſed.</hi> Even ſo ſay men in theſe daies, of the naked truths and waies of God: do any of the Rulers or Nobles, or do the great &amp; learned Doctors &amp; famous Divines: imbrace and practice theſe ſtrict and rugged waies, but onely a companie of <hi>Browniſts,</hi> who are the baſe and obſcure fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes of the world, and a companie of fooliſh ſinguler people, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning and cenſuring all beſides themſelues, as though none ſhould be ſaved but they onely.</p>
            <p>To you: Oh yee ſpirituall blind people, whoſe vnderſtandings are darkned with the ſmoake of the bottomleſſe pitt, and whoſe braines are intoxicated and drunke with the glittering and gilded Cup of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall fornication &amp; abhomination, of the <hi>ſcarlet whore Reuel.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>To you J anſwere, and know you that the way to heaven is narrow and ſtraite, and Chriſts fold and flocke, but a ſmall &amp; little company in compariſon of the world, <hi>Math:</hi> 7.14. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.24. Alſo know that God hath not called many wiſe men after the fleſh, nor many migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor many noble, but God hath choſen the fooliſh things of this world, to confound the wiſe, and God hath choſen the weake things of this World, to confound the things that are mighty; and the baſe things of the World, and things which are deſpiſed, hath God cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, yea and things which are not, to bring to naught things that are; And he himſelfe gives the reaſon of it, <hi>that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26.27.28.29. And <hi>Iames</hi> tells us, that God hath choſen the poore of this World, rich in faith, and heires of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which he hath promiſed to them that love him, <hi>James</hi> 2 5.</p>
            <p>And what though the Rabbies and great Doctors be learned, yet it is but Earthly and humane learning, which <hi>Paul</hi> had before his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, for he was a Phariſe brought up at the feete of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> a great learned Doctor of the Law had in reputation among all the people: <hi>Acts</hi> 5.34, and 22.3. But yet when he came to the true ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall knowledge of true ſpirituall learning indeed, which is taught to all Chriſts Schollers, leſſe or more, that are brought up in his Schoole, he renounced his humane Schollerſhip, and accounted it no better then dung or dirt, <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.5.7 8.</p>
            <p>But beſides him, we read of none of the Apoſtles, that were learned in that learning, which the blinde world accounts learning and Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerſhip,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7774:11"/>
for they were all or moſt of them poore men, brought up in obſcure and baſe callings many of them being no better then poore Fiſhermen; yet when Chriſt called them, he indued them with ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall learning, which is the true learning indeed; <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1. &amp;c. And thoſe in the new Teſtament, that are commended for their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, it was becauſe they were filled with the gifts of the Spirit, and were mighty in the Scriptures, <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.38.39. <hi>Acts</hi> 18.24. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3.7.8.10. and 14.</p>
            <p>By all which places of Scripture we ſee, that the learning which made the Apoſtles famous, was not human learning, (for none of them had it but <hi>Paul,</hi> and he renounced it,) but it was heavenly learning, which came from God, being the gift of his Holy Spirit. And for all the reſt of thoſe which they ordained (by the power and Authority which they had from Chriſt) to officiat in the Churches, and to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the ſacred and holy things of God, to his choſen and ſanctifyed ones, (for none but them have true right to Chriſts ordinances,) it was ſpirituall knowledge, divine learning, and inſight into the Scripture, which are the gifts of the ſpirit of God, as is before proved; which made them fitt for thoſe Offices, that they were choſen to by the Church, and ordained by the Apoſtles, for they were not to be <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices</hi> in the Myſteries and wayes of God, but <hi>ſound in the Faith,</hi> and alſo of a holy and Godly life and converſation, which the Apoſtle calls <hi>a good report,</hi> and to have the reſt of thoſe qualifications, which he layes downe in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>and</hi> 5. <hi>Chapters,</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> 1. And whoſoever have not theſe qualifications, are not fitt (according to the Apoſtles command there) to beare Office in the true Church, which is the ſpirituall <hi>Sion, Citty,</hi> &amp; <hi>Houſe of God; Pſal.</hi> 87.2.3. and 132.13.16. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.20.21. and 52.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9, and 12.2.</p>
            <p>Now, that Heavenly learning, and gifts of the ſpirit, which the Lord under the time of the Goſpell, doth beſtow upon his choſen and holy ones, doth fulfill the Propheſies of the Prophets in old time, who Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of the ſame things, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 44 3.4, and 54.13; <hi>Ier.</hi> 31; <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.28; ſaying: And it ſhall come to paſſe afterward, that I will poure out my ſpirit upon all fleſh, and your ſonnes and your daughters ſhall prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, your old men ſhall dream dreames, and your young men ſhall ſee viſions, and alſo upon the hand-maids in thoſe dayes will I poure out my ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Oh! the ſimplicity, ſweeteneſſe and pleaſantneſſe of the wayes of God, if we had but inlightened ſpirituall underſtandings, to ſee, behold and looke into them, which if we had, they would raviſh our ſoules, rejoyce our ſpirits, and fill our hearts full of gladneſſe; But they are ſealed and will be hid from us, till the Lord in his rich mercy &amp; loving kindneſſe, be pleaſed to anoynt our eyes with ſpirituall <hi>Eye-ſalve,</hi> and take away theſe Foggie Miſts of darkneſſe &amp; ſcales of ignorance that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7774:11"/>
hang upon our underſtandings; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. Oh! that the Lord would be pleaſed to deale ſo gratiouſly with us, that we might be fooles &amp; Idiots emptie &amp; vile in our own eyes, that ſo we might nakedly lye at the footſtoole of Ieſus Chriſt, and ſeeke for wiſedome &amp; ſpirituall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, from him, &amp; him alone, according as it is our duty &amp; the the command of wiſedome; <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.4.8, and 9. Chapters. But alas, alas, we have haughty hearts &amp; proud ſpirits our owne, and ſeeke to be ſomething in ourſelves, and doe not labour to be weaned from all things, in our ſelves, as is our duty, for we ſhould nakedly goe out of our ſelves; and this we ſhall know to be true if ever the Lord come truely and throughly to inſtruct and teach us in his ſpirituall, heavenly wiſedome; It is the greife of my ſoule, to ſee people take ſuch paines, <hi>for that which will not profitt;</hi> And <hi>to lay out their ſilver for that vvhich is not vvorth the buying;</hi> Eſay. 55.2. Beeing very zealous in profeſſing the ſeeming way of God, and yet are full of ignorance &amp; blindneſſe, in the true wayes of God, wanting that true ſpirituall ſanctifyed knowledge, and cleare inſight into the Scripture, which is taught by the ſpirit of God, that being true of them, which is ſaid in <hi>Eſay.</hi> 59. That they <hi>grope for the vvall like blinde men;</hi> yea and <hi>grope as if they had no eyes, ſtumbling at noone-day,</hi> as in the night, being in deſolate places, as dead men, not knowing that a deceived heart hath turned them aſide; being not able to ſay, that there is a lye in their right hand, as the Prophet in another place ſpeakes: But unto all ſuch in the words of the ſpirit of God, I ſay, behold all you that kindle a fire, that compaſſe your ſelves about with ſparkes, walke in the light of your fire, and in the ſparkes that you have kindled; But ſaith God, this ſhall you have of my hands; Ye ſhall lye downe in ſorrow, <hi>Eſay:</hi> 50.10.</p>
            <p>Becauſe that it is a ſhame even in the eyes of the World, for a man to be of no Religion; Therfore people take upon them the outward forme of Religion, but are deſtitute of the inward power of godlineſſe, going on in a formall way of Religion, with muddy, earthie, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanctified affections, but doe not ſtrive, ſtuddy &amp; labour, as they ought to get inward principles, &amp; true grounds in their owne ſoules, that ſo they may be built upon that ſure &amp; unmooveable foundation, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver can be ſhaken; But build upon <hi>ſand, hay and ſtubble;</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeakes; And therfore that building will come to ruine, when ſtormes &amp; Tempeſts doth ariſe, as too true experience, hath, doth &amp; will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt declare, for when men are not ſoundly ſetled in the true ways they can<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ot poſſible have that true inward peace, which God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to his faithfull ones; But their ſpirits &amp; hearts are full of feares &amp; diſtractions, in time of danger and calamity, I appeale even to the hearts and ſpirits, even of people themſelves that are not as yet convinced and ſettled in the right and true wayes of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:7774:12"/>Sure I am, I am able to ſpeake it by my ſelfe, and doe ſpeake it in the preſence of my God, who knowes my heart, and trieth my reines, <hi>Rev:</hi> 2.23. that I have found it true, by former experience; for the Spirit of God ſaith, <hi>there is no peace to the vvicked, Eſay:</hi> 48.22, and 57.21. Now, while a man is out of the true wayes of God, and is in the by-wayes of ſinne and wickedneſſe, he cannot truely according to the revealed will of God, be tearmed any otherwiſe, then a wicked man; Though notwithſtanding his ſoule may be precious to God; But we are not to judge according to the ſecret will, but only to judge accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the revealed will of God, for ſecret and hidden things belong to God, but revealed things to us and to our children, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith.</p>
            <p>But all thoſe that are members of the Kingdome of Antichriſt, (as all that ſubmit to the Prelates and their Lawes are) are out of the true wayes and pathes of God, and are in the bye and crooked way of ſin and wickedneſſe; And therefore we have no grounded warrant out of the Scripture, the revealed will of God, to judge or eſteeme of them any otherwiſe but as wicked men, who in that eſtate cannot be poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of that true and ſetled peace and ſpirituall comfort and joy, that God doth beſtow vpon his faith ſevants.</p>
            <p>Now as for the proofe of this argument, tis every branch &amp; part of it proved in the foregoing diſcourſe; but on the contrary I can truelie ſpeake it, that my ſoule had never before, that true reſt, quietneſſe, and ſweete inward ſpirituall peace: that I haue been and am ſtill poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſour of, ſince my God gaue me ſtrength, might &amp; power, to ſhake of that Antichriſtian yoake, and all communion with his lawes &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. And my ſoule is filled ſo full of true reſt and peace, that all my torments and ſufferings, and the greatneſſe and potency of my adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, the chiefe of which is the Divell the prince of this world, (work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in and by his ſonne the <hi>Prelate</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi>) doth not in the leaſt terrifie or trouble mee, but I am merry and cheerefull in the midſt of the veriety of my ſufferings, for the Lord makes me to triumph over them all, and I know and beleeue: that if all the Divels in hell, and all his Limbs vpon the earth: do bend themſelves againſt me to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw me, yet they ſhall never make me ſadd, for the Lord hath given me a cheerfull and merry heart, which whoſoever hath, <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>hath a continuall Feaſt, Prov:</hi> 15.15, nor make me feare or be affrayde of them, for God is my ſalvation, I will truſt add not be affrayde of them, for God is my ſalvation, the Lord <hi>Iehovah</hi> is my ſtrength, and my ſong, he alſo is become my ſalvation, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 12 12. And though the youths doe fainte and be weary, and the younge men utterly faile, yet they that waite upon the Lord, ſhall renew their ſtrength, they ſhall mount up with wings as eagles, they ſhall runne and not be weary, and they ſhall walke &amp; not be faint, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 40.30.31. For the Lord is a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7774:12"/>
ſtrength to the poore, a ſtrength to the needy in his diſtreſſe, a refuge from the ſtorme, a ſhadow from the heate, when the blaſt of the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible one is as a ſtorme againſt the Wall, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 25.4. and the ſpirit of God ſaith: that he will keep him in perfect peace whoſe minde is ſtaied on him, therefore in the Lord will I truſt for ever. For in the Lord Iehovah is everlaſting ſtrength <hi>Eſa:</hi> 26.3.4. and the Lord ſaith, he keeps his Church and will water it every moment leaſt any hurt it, yea J will keep it night and day ſaith he. Now I am a true member of it, and therefore haue right and ſhare of the benifitt of this promiſe, and aſſuredly knowe that the Lord will ſo keep me (though I be in the midſt of the fire) that mine enemies ſhall not prevaile nor hurt mee, &amp; though all men forſake me, yet hee will take care of me and provide for me: the young lions ſhall want &amp; ſuffer hunger, but they that loue and feare the Lord, ſhall want no good thing.</p>
            <p>But my loving friend, am I become your enemy (becauſe in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke) I haue ſpoken the truth, let not your anger and diſpleaſure be further incenſed againſt me, when you haue read this that is here writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; J hope you would not haue me, who haue begun in the ſpirit, to be made perfect in the fleſh; Oh God forbid that ever I ſhould ſo much as entetaine the leaſt thought of that, and therefore know that this is my ſetled reſolution, which the Lord hath wrought in my heart. And for this I will ſpend and be ſpent, and be puld in ten thouſand peices: before I will in the leaſt deny my God, and his naked truth, or the leaſt tittle of that which he himſelf by his holy ſpirit hath made known vnto me 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.10.11.14. And further knowe that all my kindred according to the fleſh, hath deſerted and forſaken me, in my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition. But if all my friends (yea and Chriſtian Brethren alſo) in the the world, ſhould be offended with me, for ſticking cloſe to my good cauſe, and if they ſhould all forſake me and leaue me naked to the world, yea though I ſtarue &amp; rott in Priſon, (as I know I ſhall not) for as long as there was a peice of bread in the bakers ſtreet, <hi>Ieremiah</hi> wanted not in his diſtreſſes, and I know <hi>Ieremiahs</hi> God is my God, &amp; wil do the like for me as he did for him, if need require. But if J ſhould be like to ſtarue in Priſon, yet wil I never in the leaſt, by the ſtrengh &amp; might of my God, feare my enemies, or loue my friends: ſo much as to deny the leaſt of his truths, for their threatnings or cruelty, or for their faunings, flattering, and deceiueable perſwaſions, for I know if my friends do leaue me and forſake me: yet the Lord will ſtand by mee, ſupport, and vphold me, in the midſt of the greateſt of my tryalls, diſtreſſes and afflictions, and in due time deliver me from the mouth of the Lyon, for he did thus with <hi>Paul,</hi> when he was to anſwer before <hi>Nero,</hi> for his and Doctrine, at which time <hi>all forſooke him,</hi> yet the <hi>Lord ſtood by him and delivered him,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4 16.17.18. And I know he will doe ſo for me too, for he hath filled my ſoule ſo full of his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7774:13"/>
ſtrength, to ſtrengthen me in my greateſt tryalls; and of his preſence &amp; comfort, to comfort me in my preſent afflictions, that I know I can liue by faith in every condition, whether in hunger of nakedneſſe in want ſcarcity, in priſon or in dungeon, or exile or in baniſhment. And in my preſent afflicted and chained condition, I haue and do poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe all that my ſoule can deſire: for I haue God &amp; Chriſt &amp; his holy ſpirit, and haue reſt, true peace and eaſe, and though I be in bonds &amp; fettered with Irons, lockes and chaines, yet I am at liberty, for my heart &amp; ſpirit is mightily inlarged, alſo I haue full ſatisfaction, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tednes, yea the world &amp; all, 1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.22.23. &amp; for my outward condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I haue not a troubled thougt about it, for it doth not in the leaſt moleſt me; for I can truly with <hi>Withers,</hi> in the beginning of his <hi>Motto;</hi> ſay;
<q>
                  <hi>Nec habeo, Nec careo, Nec curo.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>I neither haue, nor want, nor care for.</q>
            </p>
            <p>When I haue the leaſt, then I haue a feaſt; and I hauing that, I know God will cotinue it, and for my owne part, I neither long for, nor earneſtly deſire more dainties &amp; varieties then there is at a feaſt, and I feaſt every day; and therefore haue no want of good things, yea did but my enemies truely know in how rich and plentifull a condition I am in, they would bite off their fingers ends, for to heare of my proſperous and happie eſtate, in the midſt of their cruelties, for I haue found and got ſuch riches ſince J came to Priſon, that I thinke the like is not to be got abroad in the world. And of all conditions vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, in my judgement (a priſon and an afflicted condition, for the truth and cauſe of Chriſt, and the teſtimonie of a good conſcience) is the moſt happie and rich condition: for then Gods holy ones grow in I grace and Godlineſſe, like tall Ceadars in Libanon, and get great &amp; large experience of Gods goodneſſe, faithfulneſſe and kindneſſe, as I am able to ſpeake it, by grounded experience. And though my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries are learned in the Phariſeicall, Philofical, deceiuable learning of the world <hi>Act:</hi> 5.34. &amp; 22.3. compared with <hi>Phill:</hi> 3.5.8. <hi>Coll:</hi> 2. and haue ſtuddied and beat their braines, in their <hi>Vniuerſities</hi> and elſe where, for many yeares together, yet in one ſixe moneths, in a Priſon and fettered condition: I haue got more true ſpirituall learning and and knowledge, in the miſteries of Godlineſſe, then is amongſt them all; therefore when they ſent me to Priſon, they did more for me, then if they had given me ten thouſand pounds, for they haue ſent me to a heaven vpon earth: for ſo J haue found it. And ſo farr I am from being overcome, by their vnheard of cruelty (to ſubmitt and make a baſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation, as they would haue me) which they haue &amp; do ſtill exerciſe vpon me, in a high degree, that I am ten times ſtronger then I was at the firſt, and the next act of cruelty that they ſhall inflict vpon me, will make me twenty times as ſtrong as I am, and the next act of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty after that, will make wee as vnmouable as <hi>Mount Sion;</hi> which
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7774:13"/>
cannot be moved, but abideth for ever <hi>Pſal:</hi> 125. 1. <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.30. And as the hatred &amp; diſpeaſur of my friends (which is the greater tryall of the two) which J haue incurred from them by reaſon of my judgment and Conſcience, I will carrie my ſelfe by the help &amp; aſſiſtance of my God, like an innocent &amp; harmeleſſe lamb of Chriſt; yet will I never in the leaſt, either for their love or diſpleaſure, forſake or renounce the leaſt Truth, that the Lord in great mercy hath manifeſted and made known unto me; ſince I came to priſon. For before J was not only a Novice, but a very Idiot in the right wayes of God, having muddy affections, but wanted inward principles, having fiery zeale, but it was without grounded ſpirituall knowledge; But now the Lord hath made knowne to me, by his ſpirit, the way wherein to ſerve and worſhip him; And he hath made me by his power and ſtrength as unmoveable as an Iron Pillar, or a Brazen Wall; And if they doe not in matters of Religion returne unto me, J ſhall I hope fullfill that command of God given unto <hi>Ieremy in the</hi> 15. <hi>Chapt:</hi> 19. that I ſhall not in the leaſt returne unto any of them, though I be ever accounted by them as an allien and ſtranger to them.</p>
            <p>Againe, I deſire to lett you know, that upon the pillary I challenged all the Biſhopps in England to diſpute with them, upon this propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to prove the Popes power and authority from the Devill, and that their power, authority, and juriſdiction and calling, in which they ſtand at this day, is from the Pope, and ſo originally from the Devill as well as his.</p>
            <p>But theſe Epiſcopall Rabbies, who are Cheife members of the Kingdome of Darkneſſe, had no other Argument to convince me with, then to put a Gagg in my mouth, leaſt I ſhould have ſhaken the foundation of their Antichriſtian Kingdome, publickly at the Pillary, and leaſt the people (forſooth) ſhould be infected with my ſpeeches, which in their account and eſtimation, are no better then ſcandalous, factious, and ſeditious; when as indeed they were the words of nothing but the naked Truths of God, and did not in the leaſt meddle with the perſons of any, or with any temporall ſtate matters, with which I have nothing to doe and ſay unto; And therefore they could neither factious, nor ſeditious, unleſſe the Booke of God be faction and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, which were blaſphemy once to thinke; But indeed with the Prelates every thing that is ſaid or written againſt their ſpirituall Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilonian wicked Kingdome, is counted faction and ſedition; for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they have no other arguments, to maintaine their tottering and languiſhing Kingdome, but Clubb Law, that is to ſay, tyranny, blood-thirſtineſſe and cruelty; But take that Argument and Weapon away, and then a Child will diſarme them, and beare them, and take away their Weapons from them; And then to ruine and deſtruction will their decaying Kingdome come, and alſo the Weapons that J exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7774:14"/>
and perſwaded the people of God, to draw out againſt the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, thoſe Spirituall Adverſaries of the Kingdome of the Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> was not any temporall ſword or Weapon, but only the two ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſword of Gods Word, ſpoken off <hi>Hebrews</hi> 4 12. And they are more deſcribed in the ſixth of the <hi>Epheſ.</hi> Alſo the next day after my ſufferings, by Mr. <hi>Ingram</hi> the Warden of the <hi>Fleete,</hi> I ſent this Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leng in particular to the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and earneſtly intreated him, to deliver is to himſelfe, that I would diſpute with him before all the Nobles and Peeres of this Kingdome; And if I were not able to prove that his calling and power is from the Devill, I would be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to loſe my head. But I pray you, take notice of his great learned Arguments, which he uſed to confute me, and defend himſelfe, which were theſe:</p>
            <p>Let him be lockt up cloſe priſoner, in the baſeſt place in the <hi>Wards of the Fleete;</hi> for ſo runne the words of the Order; and let none come at him, leaſt he ſhould infect any of the people with his errours, and ſo be a meanes to bring ruine and deſtruction upon his ſpirituall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>Oh! Scholaſticall Arguments indeed; Alas! poore man, are your eyes ſo ſore, that they cannot endure to looke upon the Sunne, or your back ſo gawled, that you cannot endure to be touched; it ſeemes they are, or elſe you would never have been affrayde to have met a younge man in the open feild, to have tryed out the goodneſſe of your cauſe, who deſires no other Weapons againſt you but the Bible, the Word of Life, and infallible judge of all Controverſies, and the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of my Tongue, to ſpeake freely without any gagging; And yet you are affrayde, and dare not meere me in a publicke diſpute; As poore, weake and feeble men, let me ſpeake in the words of the ſpirit of God unto you, <hi>Ier:</hi> 12. if you have runne with Foote-men, and they wearied you, then how can you contend with Horſes; And if in the Land of peace, wherein you truſt, they have wearied you, how will you then doe in the ſwellings of Jordan; That is to ſay, if you be affrayde of me a younge beginner in the wayes of God; Or if you dare not venture in the Land of peace, where you have the Temporall power and ſword at command, to incounter with me a ſtripling, that never ſtudied Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, Logick, Rhetorick, nor euer was at any Vniverſity, to learne any Lattin, Greeke, or Hebrew. How will you doe in the ſwelling of Iordan, when your temporall power ſhall be taken away from you, and ſtrange men of great parts fall upon you, and make open ſpirituall warre againſt you. Surely, you will never be able to ſtand, for already your Pillars that hold up your Kingdome, are growne ſo rotten; that they cannot endure to be roughly handled or touched; And therefore without doubt ere long your building muſt needs fall, and therefore looke to your heads, and take notice, that I have given you warning
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7774:14"/>
of it, leaſt you repent when it is to late.</p>
            <p>Againe, upon Thurſday, the 17. or 18, of May laſt, I was had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Sir Iohn Bancks,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Littleton,</hi> the Kings Attourney and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciter Generall, to be examined what J ſaid at the Pillory, before whom I expreſſed my minde ſo freely, that they were willing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous that J ſhould hold my peace, and laboured with me by fleſhly Arguments, as <hi>Peter</hi> did with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to ſave my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But before them I made this challenge, and deſired them to tell it to the Biſhops, that I would diſpute with them all before my Dread Soveraigne, (whoſe faithfull, loyall, and humble ſubject I am) to prove their calling ſo farre from being of God, (as they affirme it is) that is is from the Devill; And if I were not able to prove it, (or if I delivered any thing in the proofe of it, that deſerved death,) I would not refuſe to dye, or if J held any errours, if they could by the Authority of the Scripture, confute me, I would publickly recant them. But their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; replicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this my challeng, was: Lay him faſt in Iro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chains, Armes, and Leggs, coupled together: And let him lye in them night and day; And let neither gold nor money, nor bookes, nor writings, nor any other thing be brought unto him, from his freinds; And let none come to him, to ſpeake with him; And if any come to aſke for him, take notice of their name and place of habitation, that ſo we may overcome him with crueltie and Tyrannie, and make him ſubmit, for if we doe it not by theſe meanes, he will hardly be brought unto it; And therefore <hi>Warden of the Fleete</hi> looke to it, have a ſpeciall care of him, that none come to have any talke with him, or give him any thing, that ſo we may by Tyrannie, Crueltie and Torments, overcome him, for he leads away a multitude of people, and cauſes them to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him; And he is of ſuch a lofty high ſpirit, that if he goe on in the way, he will ſpoyle our tottering Kingdome; And therefore put to your beſt aſſiſtance, to ſee if by any meanes you can overcome him, to get him to ſubmit. This was the effect of their ſpeech.</p>
            <p>Oh! Brave Epiſcopall Arguments indeed. But J pray you, did ever Chriſt or his Apoſtles, or any of his Servants, uſe any ſuch Arguments, to overcome or convince thoſe that were oppoſite to them in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? No verily; in the whole New Teſtament, we doe not read that any of Chriſts ſervants, for ſpirituall things, uſed any ſuch Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, or Clubb Arguments as theſe; for they uſed nothing but ſpirituall Weapons, to overcome ther enemies; And with the ſharpe two edged ſword of Gods Word; <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Rev:</hi> 19.15; they fought againſt their Adverſaries, by this and by this alone, they did overcome them; And <hi>Peter</hi> with this one Weapon did ſtrike downe three thouſand of them at a blow, and made them yeeld ſubjection to the Kingdome of Chriſt; <hi>Acts</hi> 2. And we never reade of any temporall Weapon that they made uſe of to defend themſelves againſt their Oppoſites;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7774:15"/>
               <hi>For,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, the Weapons of our warfar are not carnall, but mighty through God to the pulling downe of ſtrong holds, and caſting downe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations; and every high thing that exalteth it ſelfe againſt the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, &amp; bringing into captivity every thought into the obedience of Chriſt;</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.5.</p>
            <p>Theſe be the Weapons, and theſe alone of the ſervants of God; But on the contrary, the ſervants of the Devill, their Weapons are Tyrannie, crueltie, and ſhedding of blood, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. and 11.7.8. and 13.7.15.16.17. where the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, that the Beaſt (the cheife members of whom the Prelates are) ſhould make warre with the Saints, &amp; ſhould overcome them; &amp; cauſe them as many as would not worſhip the Image of the Beaſt, ſhould be killed; and that none might buy or ſell, ſave he that had the marke of the Beaſt, or the number of his name; And whether the Prelates doe not in every thing make good this portion of Scripture (for I know ſome that are excommunicated by them, and that they muſt neither buy nor ſell, nor eate nor drinke with any man) let their conſtant cruel unheard of blood-thirſtie practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, declare, witneſſe &amp; manifeſt; and therfore, Oh you Prelats, you doe plainly ſhew whoſe ſonnes &amp; ſervants you are; namely, the ſonnes &amp; ſervants of the Devill himſelfe, as Chriſt himſelf doth prove &amp; declare who hath given a lively &amp; true deſcription of the childred &amp; ſervants of the Devill, ſaying unto the Iewes, who ſought to kill him, (as the the Prelats doe his faithfull people &amp; ſervants,) who boaſted that they were Abrahams ſonnes &amp; Children; <hi>But,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if you were the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Abraham, you would do the workes of Abraham, but yee are of your father the Diuell, and the luſts of your father yee will doe. Hee was a murtherer from the beginning &amp; abode not in the truth, becauſe there is no truth in him, when he ſpeaketh a lie he ſpeaketh of his owne, for he is a lyar and the father of it; Iohn</hi> 8.39.40.</p>
            <p>Here (Oh you Prelates) Chriſt doth ſhow how his people &amp; ſervants may aſſuredly know you to be ſons &amp; ſervants of the devill; for he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes &amp; ſets you forth by two markes; firſt, the Devill is a murderer, ſo are you; therfore you are his ſonns, &amp; he is your father, for have you not taken away the lives of Gods faithfull people &amp; ſervants. Witneſſe thoſe that went to Tiburne by your procurment &amp; meanes, in <hi>Queene Elizabeths</hi> time, who were neither Traitours nor Rebels, but faithfull ſubjects, &amp; ſervants to her Majeſtie; but only they were oppoſit to your Antichriſtian &amp; Babilonian Kingdome, and therfore you cauſed them to be murdred; and more you would have murdred, but her clemencie &amp; mercy was ſuch, that ſhe would not to the full ſatiſfy your blood-thirſtie murdering deſire. Alſo have you not kept others in priſon, till you have undone them in their outward eſtats, &amp; means, that you have made them to pine away with hunger &amp; want; which the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, is a torment worſe then to be put to death by the ſword; <hi>Lament.</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:7774:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And ſome have loſt their lives by your meanes in priſon; And alſo have not ye, even ye, ſhed the blood of thoſe three worthies of the Lord on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for ſpirituall things, who were neither Traitours nor Rebels, (but faithfuller ſubjects then your ſelvs, as they have proved in their croſſe-bill againſt you) and did write nor teach, neither treaſon, ſedition, nor rebellion, but only oppoſed themſelves againſt your ungodly wicked Kingdome; The memory of that unpareleld act of crueltie, is yet freſh both in your eyes &amp; eares, the like whereof in any Chriſtian ſtate, where the goſpel hath been profeſſed, was never heard of in the world; I know others have had too deepe a hand in, being your aſſiſtants, and have condeſcended too much to your wicked deſires; But with them I will not, nor doe not in the leaſt meddle, nor have nothing to ſay to them, but pray, and deſire God to open their eyes, and to give them true repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance for their ſin, if it be his will &amp; pleaſure, &amp; ſo I leave the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>But you &amp; you only have been the originall fountaine &amp; true cauſe of all the righteous blood that hath been ſhed in this land or Kingdom, for matters of Religion &amp; conſcience, ever ſince the dayes of your firſt predeceſſour, <hi>Auſtin the Monke,</hi> (even unto this preſent houre,) who came from the bloody Citty of Rome, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. with Antichriſts Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie &amp; Law, the foundation of his &amp; your Kingdome, with excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding much blood, as we reade in <hi>Francis Godwins Cattalogue of Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops,</hi> from the 37. page to the 48. And it hath beene by you &amp; your forefathers maintained &amp; upheld by Tyrannie &amp; blood, ever ſince to this very time, as I will juſtifie it &amp; maintaine it before your faces, age after age, even unto this very day.</p>
            <p>And the foreſaid Author in that Booke, who was a Biſhop, &amp; one of your owne Creatures, for his booke of Meeters doth in part prove it; and therefore know aſſuredly, that the Lord will require the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blood of all his Saints &amp; ſervants at your hands, which you &amp; your murdering Predeceſſours, have ſpilt in abundant manner.</p>
            <p>And to me that am but a poore, weake &amp; young ſtripling, little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 20. yeares of age, who you have caſt into priſon, for a thing I was not guiltie off, as I declared before the faces of the Cheif of you; &amp; yet you have condemned me upon two falſe oaths, in which the partie, as I am able to prove, hath ſworne flatly againſt himſelfe; for in his firſt Oath he ſweareth, that I &amp; <hi>Mr. Wharton</hi> had printed <hi>Doctor Baſtwicks Bookes</hi> together; and then in his ſecond Oath he ſwore, that I did them alone; And upon theſe grounds you have exerciſed upon me ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of acts of crueltie, that the like wherof <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe among all thoſe tyrants &amp; ſtrange Beaſts, Heathens &amp; <hi>Pagans,</hi> with whom he had to deale, had never exerciſed &amp; inflicted upon him, though he was the greateſt ſufferer, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. that ever I read off; but only Chriſt, who for the ſake &amp; the ſalvation of his elect, underwent the wrath of God himſelfe, which no abſtracted Creature was able to ſtand under.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:7774:16"/>But firſt, in all <hi>Pauls</hi> ſufferings, I never reade that ever his mouth was gaged, but you have gaggd me, for ſpeaking neither lyes, faction, nor ſedition, but only the naked Truth; (the ſpace of an houre &amp; halfe) whereas if I had uttered any errours, or untruths, you being (as you ſay you are) ſpirituall Fathers, you ought there publjckly to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed me, in the preſence of the people, you cannot ſay but you heard of it, for two of the Cheife of you were in the Starr-Chamber at that time, being hard by where I ſtoode.</p>
            <p>Againe, the Heathens and <hi>Pagans</hi> would not condemne <hi>Paul,</hi> as you may reade <hi>Acts</hi> 25. till his accuſers were brought face to face, to juſtifie &amp; prove their accuſation; but you have cauſed me to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and my accuſers were never brought face to face, to juſtifie any thing againſt me.</p>
            <p>And you <hi>William Laud, Prelate of Canterburie,</hi> for ſo I call you, and will not in the leaſt revile your perſon, by calling you out of your name; You, I ſay, know very well, that in the making of my defence before the honourable Lords, I to your face did ſilence you in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the open Court, that you had not one word to ſay unto me, but ſate downe as it ſeemed to me, in a great chaffe &amp; rage, your face being as redd as the face of him, whoſe countenance did declare, your heart thirſted after my blood, and part of it you have gott, but you are never the better for it, nor I nothing the worſe for leaving of it, but much the better; for it hath beene a meanes the Lord working with it, to purge my ſoule from a great deale of corruption, &amp; droſſe, hath mightily cleared up my underſtanding, that I have gott a more true inſight by many degrees, into the true wayes of God then I had before; for I was very ignorant of them before, the ſtripes purged out my ignorance; for the eys of my underſtanding were like the eyes of the man in the Goſpell, who when Chriſt had opened them, did ſee men walking as trees afarre off; even ſo, and no better did I, for I ſaw the truths of God but darkely &amp; afarre off, in a hidden manner; but ſince that the Lord hath taken away the ſcales of ignorance &amp; blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that did hang upon my underſtanding, and hath annointed my eyes with true &amp; ſpirituall eye-ſalve, ſo that I ſee very much clearer into the pure waies of God, then I did before, for they were hidd from my eyes, but now the Lord himſelfe hath revealed them unto me; but know ye that the Lord will one day in flaming and burning fire (if you repent not, but I thinke ſome of you are paſt it, <hi>Matth:</hi> 12.31.32. <hi>Mark:</hi> 3.29.) render you a recompence, for your blood-thirſtie Tyrannie, inflicted upon me, his poore, younge and weake ſervant; But unto him I committ my ſelfe and my cauſe, knowing that ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is his, and he will repay it one day upon your heads and pates.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:7774:16"/>Againe, <hi>Paul</hi> when he was a priſoner in the Cuſtody of the very <hi>Pagans,</hi> that had nothing but the light of nature, to guide them in the wayes of God; yet notwithſtanding <hi>Felix</hi> the Governour gave com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to the Centurion, who kept <hi>Paul,</hi> that he might have liberty, and that he ſhould forbid none of his acquaintance and Freinds to come to him, and miniſter to his wants and neceſſity; <hi>Acts</hi> 24.23. alſo when he was going to Rome, priſoner, <hi>Iulius</hi> the Centurion, in whoſe Cuſtody he was, yet though he were but a Heathen, gave him liberty to goe to his freinds, to refreſh himſelfe; <hi>Acts</hi> 27 3. Yea when he was come priſoner to Rome, yet the very infidels had ſo much humanity, courteſy and mercy in them, as not to lock up <hi>Paul</hi> cloſe priſoner, in a baſe &amp; obſcure place, ſo that none might come to him, to ſpeake with him, or bring him any thing; And yet <hi>Tertullus</hi> the Orator (one of the Prelates Brethren had accuſed him for a peſtilent fellow, and a mover of ſedition among all the Iewes throughout the World, and a ring leader of the Sect of the <hi>Nazarens;</hi> Yet they let him dwell by himſelfe, with a ſouldier that kept him, two whole yeares, in his owne hired houſe, where he had libertie to receive all that came unto him, <hi>Acts the laſt Chapter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! <hi>Paul,</hi> it was well for thee, and happie waſt thou that thou hadſt to deale with <hi>Pagans,</hi> in whoſe eyes I am ſure thou didſt finde more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and mercy, then if thou waſt alive, and wert now in England in the like caſe, ſhouldſt finde at the hands of thoſe that are Chriſtians, in name and boaſt; And ſay of themſelves, that they are thy ſucceſſors, but are indeed &amp; in truth, the Diſciples of the Devill &amp; Antichriſt, as I have already proved, for thongh all the Prelates in England were not able, having no grounded ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to make ſuch an accuſation againſt me as <hi>Tertullus</hi> did againſt <hi>Paul;</hi> Yet for all that have they cauſed me to be laid in fetters and locks of Iron, in a cloſe roome lockt up cloſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, from the ſociety of any; Commanding that none ſhould be admitted to com to me, to ſpeak with me, nor to bring me any thing; Alſo they are ſo farre from letting me to have libertie to goe and ſee my freinds, as <hi>Paul</hi> had; That they will not ſo much as with a Keeper ſuffer me to walke a little in the priſon-Yard, to take a little aire for my refreſhing; my health being impaired for want of aire, and ſtirring my ſelfe, which I cannot in the leaſt doe, without much trouble, by reaſon of my Irons; And I have beene lockt up cloſe priſoner about 4 Moneths, and not ſuffered in the leaſt to ſtirr out of my lodging; but when they had me forth before the Majeſtrate; Yea the Warden of the <hi>Fleete</hi> hath denied me penn, inke and paper, only to write a ſhort petition to the Lords of the Counſell, (in the preſence of my Keeper) that J might have but ſo much libertie as to take a little aire in the narrow Yard, in the common Iayle, for my refreſhing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:7774:17"/>Oh! all you Chriſtian eares that heare of theſe things, ſtand amaized and wonder at the blood-thirſty, vnparaleld crueltie and tyranny of the Biſhops, which they haue cauſed to be inflicted vpon me, and had no grounded cauſe originally for to do it, but onely hearing that I ſet my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace towards <hi>Sion,</hi> as one of the Lambes of Chriſt: therefore theſe devouring wolves <hi>Math.</hi> 7.15. &amp; craftie ſubtile foxes <hi>Cant.</hi> 2 15. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13 4. haue hunted and thirſted after my blood, part of which they haue gott and yet are not ſatisfied, but longe to pick my carkeiſes &amp; bones. Now we do not read of the like cruelty inflicted vpon any of the Apoſtles or their followers, in all the New Teſtament, by any of thoſe (Tirants, Pagans, Infidels &amp; Heathens) that perſecuted them, which they have cauſed to be inflicted vpon me; whom they are not able juſtlie to accuſe, of the breach of the leaſt Commandement or lawes, of God or the King; though I do confeſſe with David, that J haue ſecret ſinnes <hi>Pſalme</hi> 19.20. and with Paul that I haue a body of ſinne within me <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23.24. Yet I can ſay in the preſence of my God, and ſpeake the words of truth, that I do deſire and labour to be cleanſed from them all.</p>
            <p>Alſo I haue challenged them to diſpute with them for my life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King, to prove their Calling to be from the Divell, and if I were erronious, &amp; if they by Gods word could confute me, I would recaunt publickly.</p>
            <p>But their ſureſt pley and infallible Arguments to convince me, was Clubb-Law, that is to ſay, take him Iaylour, and lay him in Irons, in the obſcureſt and baſeſt place in your priſon, and let the ſtone Walls and iron grates convince him, for we dare not meete him in the plaine feild, in a publick diſpute, though he be but an unlearned youth; And if it be poſſible, keepe him in darkneſſe and obſcuritie; And if you can doe it handſomely, that the World can take no notice of it, ſtarve him, for we command you to let nothing be brought unto him.</p>
            <p>Oh! you Satyrs, Vultars, Owles, and Scritch-Owles, for ſo the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt calls you, <hi>Eſay:</hi> 13. <hi>two laſt verſes. Eſay:</hi> 34.14.15. <hi>Rev:</hi> 18.2. The Roman ſpirituall State, being that Cage of filthineſſe, that holds you, who are, as the Holy Ghoſt there ſpeakes, a Company of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, Devils, and foule Spirits.</p>
            <p>Oh! you Night-Owles and Birds of Darkneſſe, and uncleanes, that dare not come to ſhow your crooked faces in the bright Sun-ſhining light and cleare Cryſtall glaſſe of Gods ſacred and unſpotted Truth; It ſheweth &amp; demonſtrateth to all the World, that you are a Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of deformed Creatures, and Sonnes of Darkneſſe, impiety, wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; ungodlineſſe; Or elſe you would lay aſide your Cowardly Clubb-Arguments, and come into the face of the open Sunne, that there you may be ſeene, whether you be rotten or ſound, or whether you be true gold or nothing but durt &amp; droſſe, which is good for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7774:17"/>
but the dunghill, or whether your Kingdome be the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt, or the Kingdome of the Divell, for of neceſſity it muſt be one of theſe, for there is no more ſpirituall Kingdomes in the world but theſe two. Or whether you your ſelves be ſervants of Chriſt, or the ſervants and true ſubjects of the Divell. But your hating of the truth and blaſpheaming of it, calling it the Refuge of Heritickes, as you did in your open Court, at the Cenſure of that worthy Doctour, <hi>Doctour Iohn Baſtwicke.</hi> And alſo your hating and bloody perſecuting of them that loue it, doth vndenyably declare and manifeſt what you are, and of whom your Kingdom doth depend. For Chriſt ſaith every one that doth evill hates the ſight, neither cometh to the light, leaſt his deedes ſhould be reproved <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.20. Truely you plainelie ſhew, that you are men of darkneſſe, and workers of wickednes and iniquitie, for you cannot endure the light, for it is too cleare &amp; too bright for you, to come nakedlie and openlie and ſhew your ſelues before it; becauſe you are men of darkneſſe and evill doers, and therefore you hate the light; but if you were men that were workers of righteouſneſſe, and walked in the waies of truth, you would not be affraide to be tried by the light of it, but would deſire to be brought vnto it. And in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer place Chriſt ſaith, <hi>he that doth truth cometh to the light, that his deeds may be made manifeſt,</hi> that they are wrought in God; and therefore to conclude this point, I will ſay no more then Chriſt ſaith, you may know the tree by the fruit, <hi>for a bad tree doth not bring forth good fruit, nor a good tree corpupt fruit Math.</hi> 7.18. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.43. But to goe backe againe to <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. In the ſecond place, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The Divell abode not in the truth, becauſe there is no truth in him, when he ſpeaketh a ly he ſpeakth it of his owne for he is a lyar and the father of it.</hi> Here Chriſt ſhewes that the Children of the Divell abide not in the truth, but haue their ſoules filled with lyes. And whether you the <hi>Prelates</hi> be not ſuch, I appeale even to your owne writings, ſayings &amp; doeings, the moſt of whoſe writings are ſtuffed with many vntruths, having almoſt as many lies in them as pages. And for the vntruths de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in your Court Sermons, Worthy <hi>Doctour Baſtwicke</hi> in the third part of his <hi>Letany,</hi> hath painted out in there colours, yea what damnable Doctrines are there taught (ſaving ſome few) agreeing with the Filthy Whore &amp; Strumpet of <hi>Rome,</hi> as that forenamed Doctour doth proue in the ſecond part of his <hi>Letany,</hi> with which he doth moſt truely paralel you, that you are in a manner both of one corruption, yea among all the reſt he there proues; that you hold and maintaine that monſtrous and horrable Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> that is to ſay: That the Body of Chriſt, is reallie, corperallie, and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiallie in the Sacrament of his Supper. And this alſo may be proved out of the great <hi>Prelats</hi> ſpeech, made before the honorable Lords, at the Cenſure of the three late worthies. Yea whole Vollumes may be made,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7774:18"/>
of thoſe damnable Doctrins that you hold, &amp; are not aſhamd to publiſh them to the view of the whole world <hi>(Cum Privilegio)</hi> eſpecialy in your late printed Bookes. By all which you proue &amp; make good this por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Scripture; that you are of your father the Divell, becauſe you do not abide in the truth, but ſpeake, preach, write and maintaine falſe lies, wicked and damnable Doctrines.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I by the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of my God, a litle deciphered you in a brief way. But it may be, you will be like a neſt of <hi>Waſps,</hi> which being ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red will flie about my eares, with your Scorpion ſtings, but if you do, it will manifeſt you to be part of thoſe <hi>Locuſts</hi> (as you are indeede and in truth) <hi>that came out of the bottomleſse pitt Revel.</hi> 9.2.3. of whom the Hoy Ghoſt ſaith; that they had tailes like <hi>Scorpions,</hi> and there were ſtings in there tailes, <hi>and they had power to hurt men verſe</hi> 10. But be it known vnto you, that I am not in the leaſt affraid of you, for I nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther feare an Axe at Tower hill, nor a Stake in Smithfield, nor a-Halter at Tyburne, nor Whipping at a Carts-arfe, nor a Pillary in the Pallice-yard nor Gagging, nor Cutting of eares and noſe, nor Burning in the forehead or cheeks, nor yet Baniſhment with <hi>Iohn</hi> to <hi>Pathmos.</hi> For I verilie beleeve if you ſhould ſend me thither, I ſhall there finde Chriſt, which by his ſpirit will vnfold the Revelation vnto me, and then J would write it and ſend it abroad into the world, and it would vex you as ill, as Sampſon did the Philiſtims, &amp; proue as fatall to your decaying, tottering, ſpirituall Babilonian Antichriſtian King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as his Foxes with fire-brands at their tailes, were to the Philiſtims Corne. And therefore as you loue your almoſt ruinated Kingdome, looke to it, and knowe that the faſter you kicke, the harder I will ſpurre you, &amp; the more you fling, the cloſer will I ſticke &amp; cleave faſt vnto you; for you are plants (which I groundedly know) the Lord never planted, &amp; therfore vndoubtedly he will plucke you up <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.13. And therefore by the might, power and ſtrength of my God, <hi>Pſal</hi> 118.14. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 12.2. who is the worker of all my works in mee and for mee, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 26.12. For I am reſolved come life, come death, ſeeing you by force &amp; crueltie haue called me to it, to ſhewe my ſelfe valiant for the truth of God, <hi>Ier.</hi> 9.3.</p>
            <p>I alreadie made three Challenges to diſpute with you, but you are ſo Cowardlie, that you dare not to come into the plaine and open field, but you fight with tyrant-like weapons, namelie: with crueltie. And therefore to ſee whether you haue any manhoode in you or noe, J make &amp; ſend forth this fourth Challenge, to you Biſhops &amp; Prelates, which is this.</p>
            <p>That I will (if you pleaſe) diſpute with you all, face to face, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King and State, for life and libertie; vpon theſe enſueing Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:7774:18"/>Firſt, To proue that the Popes Power is from the Divell.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That your Calling, Power, Authoritie &amp; Iuriſdiction, is from the Pope.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That all Gods people, are bound vnder paine of eternall damnation, to withdraw their ſpirituall obedience and ſubjection, from your ſpirituall law and Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Now vnpon theſe propoſitions will I diſpute with you all, and venter life for life, before the King and State, vpon theſe tearmes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That you ſhall lay aſide Club-Arguments, which is take him Iaylour, and lay him in Irons, and locke him up cloſe Priſoner, and keep him in ſafe cuſtodie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That the Booke of God, which is an infallible truth, ſhall be the ſole Iudge of the Controverſie</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That J may haue libertie, without being Gagged, to ſpeake my minde freelie and boldlie.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That J may haue the vſe of ſome books which I ſhall chuſe. And if you dare gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me theſe 4 things, if I be not able to proue all the fore ſaid Poſitions, by demonſtrable and vndeniable arguments, that you ſhall not be able in the words of truth to gainſay or deny the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I wil be willing to loſe my head and life, therefore take notice of what J haue now the fourth time ſaid and challenged you to your faces, (for I intend to ſend you this) that in the preſence of the King and Nobles you will make it good, and therefore if you be not Cowards, fitt your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to come into the open pitched field face to face.</p>
            <p>Alſo be it knowne vnto you, that I will at <hi>Pauls Croſſe,</hi> diſpute with all your <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> vpon theſe Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That they are all of them, Servants &amp; Miniſters of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That in the place and ſtanding they are now in, at this preſent, they haue no authority from God to preach his word, nor adminiſter any of his ſacred ordinances to the peole, nor the people any ground or warrant out of the word of God, to heare the word from, or pertake with them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That the Church of England as at this day it ſtands, is An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian, both in Power, in Matter, in Miniſtrie, in Forme and in Woſhirppe.</p>
            <p>Fourrhly, That all Gods people are bound in duty &amp; conſcience, to ſeparate away from it, &amp; to haue no communion with it.</p>
            <p>All which things, if J be not able to proue againſt them all, laying aſide (as I ſaid before) all Club law, and letting the word of God be the ſole Judge of the controverſie; I will be bound to preach a Recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Sermon in every Citty in the Kingdome.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN LILBURNE.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
